A Guide to the Papers of Ambrose Bierce, 1842-1914
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Scrapbook Series
  - Volume 13, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 11)
    Although many items lack mastheads, and some miscellaneous articles are included, most of the clippings appear to be Bierce's titled columns: [MSS # 5992-a]
    - "Fables and Anecdotes"
      p.26
    - "Little Johnny"
      p.2-89
    - "The Passing Show"
      p.1
    - "Prattle"
      p.92-131, 133-135, 137, 139, 142-143, 145
  - Volume 14, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 11)
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. Of the dated items, the earliest is 1892 Dec 4 (p.77); the latest is 1897 Aug 15 (p.28). Although many items lack mastheads, and some miscellaneous articles are included, most of the clippings appear to be Bierce's titled column: [MSS # 5992-a]
    - "Prattle"
      p. 1-148
  - Volume 15, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 12)
    Pagination added: 1-146
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. OF the dated items, the earliest is 1890 Oct 5 (p.97); the latest is 1897 May 30 (p.76).
    Although many items lack mastheads, and many miscellaneous articles are included ( e.g., "One Way to be ridiculous," p.105), most of the clipping sappear to be Bierce's titled columns: [MSS # 5992-a]
    - "The Passing Show"
      p.2-22, 24
    - "Prattle"
      p.23, 26-146
    - "Fables without Morals"
      p.74
  - Volume 16, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 12)
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. Of the dated items, the earliest is 1899 Nov 26 (p.145); the latest is 1906 Jun 13 (p.1).
    Pagination added: 1-150. Although many items lack mastheads, and some miscellaneous articles are included, most of the clippings appear to be Bierce's titled columns: [MSS # 5992-a]
    - "A Cynic's Dictionary"
      p.132-136, 148, 150
    - "Fables and Anecdotes"(etc.)
      p.123, 124, 126-128, 130, 131, 137
    - "Hamlet fro Outward..."
      p.28, 34
    - "Little Johnny"
      p.29, 46, 50-125
    - "solioguies of the Great"
      p.15
    - "The Passing Show"
      p.137-146, 148-150
    - "The Views of One"
      p. 1-46, 133
    - "Unauthenticated Dialogues"
      p.35
  - Volume 17, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 13)
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. Of the dated items, the earliest is 1892 Feb 13 (p.53); the latest is 1915 Feb-(p.115). [MSS # 5992-a]
    - Primarily, this volume contains miscellaneous clippings, including editorial articles re: [California] politics and articles about Bierce and his work, for example
      - "A Strange Rebirth"
        p.36, 41
      - "A Caustic Critic"
        p.51
      - "Forman on Bierce"
        p.53
      - "The American Kipling"
        p.130
      - "The Cult of bierce"
        p.132
      - "America's Greatest Poet/Poem"
        p.54, 55, 60, 61, 63-64, 67
    - Bierce's titled columns are included, although some clippings lack mastheads:
      - "Ambrose Bierce Says"
        p.93, 95
      - "Fables and Anecdotes"(etc.)
        p.49, 58, 59
      - "Little Johnny"
        p.10, 29, 65, 68, 101-104, 106
      - "Soliloquies of the Great"
        p.117
      - "The Passing Show"
        p.108-129
      - "Prattle"
        p.70-92, 107
      - "Unauthenticated Dialogues"
        p.107
    - As well as revies of Bierce's books:
      - "Can Such Things Be"
        p.145
      - "Shapes of Clay"
        p.43
      - "The Collected Works..."
        p.60, 111
      - "The Cynic's Work Book"
        p.143, 144
      - "The Monk and the..."
        p.144-149
  - Volume 18, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 13)
    Pagination added: 1-143 (p. 1 is blank)
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. Of the dated items, the earliest is 1882 Jan 6 (p.82); the latest is 1915 Jul 4 (p.18). [MSS # 5992-a]
    - Although many items lack masteads, most appear to be Bierce's titled columns:
      - "A Spread of Quick-Lunch..."
        p.120, 121, 125
      - "Ambrose Bierce Says"
        p.52-57, 60, 67, 73
      - "The Bald Campaigner"
        p.110
      - "Certain Fool Epigrams..."
        p.120, 122
      - "Hamlet for Outward..."
        p.115, 116
      - "Prattle"
        p.2-16, 48, 118, 124
      - "The Curmudgeon..."
        p.119
      - "The elancholy Author"
        p.111, 115
      - "The Passing Show"
        p.22-49, 88, 90, 92-97
      - "Unauthenticated Tales"
        p. 3, 37, 74, 81, 111, 125, 128, 133
      - "The Views of One"
        p.58, 62-66, 68-69, 72-73, 75, 78-83, 85-89, 92
    - As well as revies of Bierce's books: Reviews of Bierce's books:
      - "Can Such Things Be"
        p.49, 80, 142
      - "The Collected Works..."
        p.141
      - "The Monk and the ..."
        p.80
      - "The Shadow of the Dial"
        p.19, 129, 130, 137, 139
      - "Shapes of Clay"
        P.10, 46
      - "Write it Right"
        p.19, 132, 140
    - Additionally, this volume contains miscellaneous clippings, including articles about Bierce and his work, for example, "Ambrose Bierce-A Strange Rebirth" (p.134, 135) and an obituary re: his brother, Albert (p.101), as well as a number of articles re:
      - Bierce's disappearance in Mexico: p.18, 10, 84, 122, 126, 127, 131, 137
  - Volume 19, Black cloth-bound blank book (36 * 25 cm.), embossed on the cover, "Scrap Book" in gold above a decorative device. Although some clippings are annotated in Bierce's hand, this volume was compiled posthumously. (Box 14)
    Pagination added: 1-119
    Most items lack dates, and those that are dated are not in chronological order. Of the dated items, the earliest is 1892 Apr 13 (p.30); the latest is 1915 Oct 30 (p.77, 94). [MSS # 5992-a]
    - Primarily, this volume contains miscellaneous clippings by Bierce re: literary criticism, and articles about Bierce and his work. Although, some items lack mastheads, Bierce's titled columns are included:
      - "A Cynic's Dictionary"
        p.82
      - "Little Johnny"
        p.92, 95
      - "The Views of One"
        p.114
      - "Unauthorized Tales"
        p.91
    - and reviews of Bierce's books:
      - "Can Such Things Be"
      - "In the Midst of Life"
        p.86, 91, 97, 110
      - "The Collected Works..."
        p.63
      - "Write it Right"
        p.76, 93, 110, 112, 115, 118
    - Mounted on pages 44-47 are several typed manuscripts:
      - Typed manuscripts:, The published text of the last item may be found in v.16, p.138).
        A Hope of Reform, A Faulty Rigging, Ah said the mole..., The Vigilant Guardian, Bullet & Bone, King and Parrot, and The Lady and the Tiger.
    - This volume also contains a number of articles re:
      - Bierce's disappearance in Mexico:
        p.14, 15, 18, 20, 35, 37, 48, 49, 58-62, 65-68, 74, 75, 77-79, 81-85, 89, 90, 93-96, 99, 107-109, 111, 112, 118
  - Volume 20 (Box 14)
    This "volume" actually consists of a brown envelope containing loose printed articles clipped from various magazines that were probably not pasted in the scrapbooks because the text appears on both sides of the leaves.
    The items have been numbered and the item numbers appear at the foot of each frame. [MSS # 5992-a]
    - The clippings have been arranged in the below-listed catagories.
      - Articles and stories by Ambrose Bierce
      - Articles by others concerning Ambrose Bierce
      - Articles in which Bierce is mentioned
      - Book Reviews and Miscellaneous items.
    - Articles and Stories by Ambrose Bierce
      - The Conflagration in Ghargaroo." publ: Cosmopolitan Magazine1906 Feb.
      - "Have We a Navy?" publ: Everybody's Magazine
        1906 Oct.
      - ["Little Johnny"](corrected proof-text unidentified) n.d., publ. n.p.
      - "The Monk and Hangman's Daughter"(frag.) n.d., publ: Neale's Monthly
      - [Series of 4 vignettes] 1907 May, publ: n.p.
        - "Friendship" n.d., publ: n.p.
        - "If Reform Reformed" n.d., publ: n.p.
        - "Nature as a Reformer" 1908 June, publ: n.p.
        - "Some Neglected First Principles"
      - "Small contributions-An Execution in Batrugia" 1907 May, publ: n.p.
      - Small Contributions-Rose-water Penology/Looking Downward/The Writers Written" 1907 Aug., publ: n.p.
      - "Small Contributions-The Writer folk" 1909 Feb, publ: n.p.
      - "Small Contributions-The Reversion to Barbarism/The Writer Folk", publ: 1909 Mar
    - Articles by Others Concerning Ambrose Bierce
      - "About Ambrose Bierce" by [_]. 1904 Jan., publ: The Goose-Quill
      - "Ambrose Bierce-Satrist" by Democritus. 1908 Nov. 28, publ: Town Talk
      - "Bierce, Kipling, Popularity and Criticism-II" by Robert Barr. 1907 Nov., publ: The Pacific Monthly
      - "Literature and its Master" by [_]. (incomplete) 1908 June, publ: Everyman
      - "Poetics, Bierce and Sterling" by Porter Garnett. 1907 Nov., publ: The Pacific Monthly
      - "Rare Bierce Items" by James D. Hart. n.d., publ: The Argonaut
      - "Satire and the Satirist" by Herman Scheffauer. n.d., publ: The Mirror
      - "Short Story Masterpieces" by Edgar White, introducing "The Damned Thing"(frag.)
      - "Short Story Masterpieces" by [_], introducing "My Favorite Murder(frag) 1907 Jan., publ: The Story Book(?)
      - "The Wine of Wizardry/The Rape of the Muse" by [_](re: George Sterling's poem and Bierce's commentary). 1907 Oct., publ: The Little Devil
      - "Pomegranates and Lemons" by [_] re: George Sterling's poem "The Wine of Wizardry" and Bierce's commentary. 1907 Oct., publ: Humanity
      - "Our Greatest Poet?" Michael Monahan. (re: George Sterling's poem "The Wine of Wizardry and Bierce's commentary). 1907 Oct., publ: The Papyrus
      - "The Great American Poem Reviewed" by Harry Esty Dounee (re: George Sterling's poem "The Wine of Wizardry" and Bierce's commentary). 1907 Nov., publ: Hamilton Literary Magazine
    - Articles in which Bierce is mentioned
      - "An 'Impressionist' Estimate of Current Literary Values in America" by [_](incomplete). n.d. (see p. 632), publ: Current Literature
      - "Chronicle and Comment" by [_]. 1913 Aug. (see p. 593), publ: The Bookman
      - "The Golden Story of California" by Newton Dent. 1906 Nov. (see p. 156, 161), publ: Munsey's Magazine
      - "Literature: Some Aspects in West" by Porter Garnett. 1907 FEb. (see p. 218, 221), publ: Pacific Monthly
      - "The Men Who Make Our Books" by Elizabeth Vore. 1903 Apr. (see p. [4], [7]), publ: Overland Monthly
      - "Notes (Mostly Bubble and Squeak)" by [_]. 1900 Mar. 15 (see p.46), publ: The Goose-Quill
      - "The Railroad Machine as it Works Now" by Charles Edward Russell. 1910 Sep., publ: Hampton's Magazine
        (recaps Bierce's campaign v. Huntington)
      - "San Francisco" by [_]. 1906 Aug., publ: The Golden Elk
        (see p.16)
      - "San Francisco" by William Marion Reedy. [1906]Nov., publ: The FRA
        (see p. 52)
      - "San Francisco Fallen" by William Marion Reedy. 1906 June., publ: National Magazine
        (see p. 244)
      - "A Story of Three States" by Alfred Matthews. 1902 May, publ: Scribner's Magazine
        (see p. 570)
      - "White Cottages" by [_]. n.d., publ: n.p.
        (re: Bierce's home)
    - Book Reviews and Miscellaneous (items 35-41)
      - Prospectus advertisement re: The Colleted Works...", publ: Neale Publishing Co."
      - Review of The Devil's Dictionary by Benjamin Decasseres. 1942 July 25., publ: Washington Times Herald
      - Review of In the Midst of Life by [_]. 1918 Aug. 4, publ: The Times Lit[erary Suppl]
      - Poem "Jonathan Stone" by Edwin Steele. 1894 May, TM
      - Form letter, 1903 May 22, Oscar T. Shuck to Bierce with list of "California Books offered for sale. 1903 May 22
      - Empty envelope origionally containing book reviews (list in Bierce's hand)
      - Unidentified/unrelated/unmatched fragments, including:
        - "The Statue of Grief at Stanford University, California" by William Bittle Wells/
        - "The Destruction of San Franscisco" by [_]. (frag)/
        - "The Reconstruction of San Franscisco" by [_]. (frag)/
        - "The Story of the Bulletins" by Van. W. Anderson./
        - "The Relief Work at Portland Oregon' by Sidona V. Johnson. (frag) 1906 June., publ: Pacific Monthly
        - "San Francisco" by Jaquin Miller. n.y. June/July, publ: Sunset, four miscellaneous leaves
    - Photo of Ambrose Bierce & Squirrel on park bench (Box 14)